Carlos Utrilla Guerrero

Nonnelveld 79, 4811HN – Breda, The Netherlands

1 +34 629954470 • Torcid.org/0000-0002-9994-1462

1 https://carlosug.github.io/

Education

Universidad Politécnica de Madrid, ES

Since Oct 2023

PhD candidate in Artificial Intelligence, Ontology Engineering Group (OEG): Web

University of Manchester, UK

2014

M.Sc. in Social Research Methods and Statistics (CMI): Web 🜎 , tesis:Link 🌎 – Assignments: Link 🌎

University of Zaragoza, ES

2011

BA in Business and Administration, Erasmus Programme, Odense, DK (6 Months, 2012)

Research Interests

Open-source scientific research software, language language models, semantic web and bioinformatics

Career Profile

Research software engineer, researcher and project manager

Computer Skills

Languages: Python, R, TypeScript (React, ExpressJS, NextJS), LaTeX, SQL

Web: SPARQL, RDF, ontologies (OWL, SKOS, SIO), OpenAPI, JSON, XML, HTML&CSS, Material UI, D3.js

Tools: Bash, Git, Jupyter, Rstudio, Linux, Neo4J, Protégé, Docker

Languages

Spanish (Mother tongue), English (Fluent), French (Intermediate), Dutch (Basic)

Work Experience

Research Data & Software Services, TU Delft University, Delft, NL

Since Nov 2022

 $Teacher\ \ \ \ Lesson\ \ developer$

Participate in TU Delft Digital Competence Center (DCC), Library and 4TU educational & research activities

Institute of Data Science, Maastricht University, Maastricht, NL

2020 - 2022

Researcher data scientist

Provided a diverse support in teaching and research obligations

Kleos Space S.A, Luxembourg, LU

2018 - 2019

 $Data\ scientist$

Provided support in data management and statistical analysis on the European Space Agency projects

Kneip Communications, Luxembourg, LU

2015 - 2018

 $Data\ manager$

Participated in data governance for the Financial knowledge base

European Investment Bank (EIB), Luxembourg, LU

2014

Graduate research assistant (6 months)

International scholarship in the IT department focused in data modeling, definition and implementation

Imagniarium Group S.A, Instanbul, TR

2013

Trainee data analyst (8 months)

International scholarship in a retail company to develop and implement the Forecasting Model

Association of Young Entrepreneurs of Zaragoza, Zaragoza, ES

2010

Bachelor trainee marketing (8 months)

Scholarship in a Spanish public administration to monitor the operational cash-flow and write the annual budgeting

Ibercaja saving Bank, Zaragoza, ES

2010

Bachelor trainee finance (6 months)

Scholarships in a Spanish bank to study the probability of default using logistic regression

Research Projects and Activities

Research Projects:

- 2024: ReSUF Towards a Research Software Understanding Framework for Open Science: Link
- 2023: SoSS Scientific open-source Software knowledge graph Link
- 2022: PLAYFAIR Applying data science for digital collections Link
- o 2022: DSRI Data Science Research Infrastructure Supercomputing Link 🌎
- 2022: KG4FOOD Knowledge graphs for Nutritional data Link
- 2022: ODISSEI Developing distributed analytics techniques Link
- 2021: CDDI Community Data Driven Insights Link
- 2020: EOSC-Life FAIRAssist and Training Link

Research Activities::

- o Miembro de FAIR4RS y PRO4RS en Research Data Alliance
- o Miembro de DKG en COST Action EU
- \circ Other contributions click here: https:/carlosug.github.io/research projects.pdf

Teaching Experience

- 2024, 2023: Graduate school: Digital skills for research data and software: https://carlosug.github.io/courses
- 2020; 2021; 2022: Master course: Applied Research II: https://maastrichtu-ids.github.io/AppliedRR/
- 2020; 2021, 2022: Bachelor course: Quantitative Research Methods. https://maastrichtu-ids.github.io/global-studies/

List of Publications

- C Utrilla Guerrero, Oscar Corcho and Daniel Garijo (2024). "Automated Extraction of Research Software Installation Instructions from README Files: An Initial Analysis" https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-65794-88
- C. Utrilla Guerrero, Maria Vivas Romero, Mark Dolman and Michel Dumontier (2022). "FAIR begins at home: Implementing FAIR via the Community Data Driven Insights". \(\begin{array}{c}\) https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.07429\)
- Leyla Jael Castro, Thomas Pronk, C. Utrilla Guerrero and Jürgen Windeck (2023). "Five Minutes to Write a Software Management Plan". https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6588450
- C. Utrilla Guerrero and V. Emonet (2022). "Challenges and solutions towards building and visualising FAIR data for traditional games". Storytelling DARIAH Annual Event. Athens, GR. \(\bigop\) https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6588450

Selected Awards and Scholarships

2021: Research Fellowship grant in the national infrastructure CLARIAH Research Fellows 2021. *Budget 15K euros* 2013: Leonardo Da Vinci Global Scholarship from Spain's Ministry of Education

Volunteer Experience

2010: European Volunteer Service (7 months) - Turkiye I.S.I. Tme Engelliler Spor Federasyonu, Ankara, TR

Presentations and Talks

Invited talks and conferences:

- o 2023: Machine-actionable Software Management Plans Mini-Hackathons, ZB Med in Cologne, (DE) 🌎 Web
- o 2023: Teaching Reproducible Research and Open Science Conference, Sheffield University, (UK) • Web
- o 2022: Storytelling DARIAH Annual Event 2022, Athens, (GR) Material
- o 2022: Metadata 4 DKE 2022, Lyon, (FR) https://cost-dkg.github.io/metadata4dkg2022/
- 2022: FAIR Coffee Lectures, Maastricht, (NL) □ Material

Workshops:

- o 2024: Workshop on GenAI for research software at TU Delft. https://zenodo.org/records/11492084
- o 2021: Workshop on FAIR Essentials. https://github.com/MaastrichtU-IDS/fair-workshop
- o 2021: Workshop on semantic web DOAP https://github.com/MaastrichtU-IDS/doap-workshop
- o 2021: Coding for researchers in Python https://github.com/MaastrichtU-IDS/coding4all

Interests

Sports: Tennis, Padel, Swimming

Others: Open source enthusiast, Traveling, History and Cooking